A Guide to the John Williamson Palmer Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8099-a
John Williamson Palmer Collection 1857-1898, n.d.
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8099-a
41 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [1963] 1970 August 19
Item Listing
- Letters
  - William Henry Hurlbert to John Williamson Palmer, 1857 Jan 29; ALS, 3 p.
    [Praises Palmer for the idea of a collection of poems and mentions George Darley. ] w/typed transcript
  - Parke Godwin to John Williamson Palmer, 1857 Jan 30; ALS, 2 p.
    [Approves proposed collection of Palmer's writings.]
  - Charles A[nderson] Dana to John Williamson Palmer, 1857 Feb 4; TL (transcript), 1 p.
    [Approves suggested publication of an illustrated edition of "Folk Songs."]
  - James T. Fields to John Williamson Palmer, 1858 Mar 1; TL (transcript), 1 p.
    [Approves his collection of autographic poems; confirms ownership of "Abou ben Adam"; refers to Palmer's admirer, the "Auyocrat [sic] of the Breakfast Table ( Oliver Wendell Holmes)."]
  - Horace Greeley to [ John Williamson Palmer], 1859 Mar 4; TL (transcript), 1 p.
    [Makes an appointment with Palmer to discuss his article on Appleton's Cyclopaedia.]
  - Jules Michelet to John Williamson Palmer, 1860 Mar 17; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Thanks Palmer for the honor done his book by its English translation.], in French, with a typed English transcript
  - Jules Michelet to John Williamson Palmer, 1860 Apr 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks Palmer for his expression of sympathy; refers to his American in-laws; and mentions [Matthew Fontaine] Maury. ] in French with a typed English transcript
  - F. E. Longfellow to John Williamson Palmer, 1860 Nov 12; TL (transcript), 1 p.
    [Thanks him for the illustrated song book.]
  - Matthew Fontaine Maury to James Croxall Palmer, 1860 Dec 20; TL (transcript), 1 p.
    [Refers to biographical notes about himself in
    Southern Literary Messenger
    ,
    Allibone's Dictionary
    and
    New America Encyclopedia
    . ]
  - James C. Palmer to John Williamson Palmer, 1860 Dec 21; ALS, 2 p.
    [Refers to Matthew Fontaine Maury's pedigree and John Williamson Palmer's article in the
    Inquirer
    on "Free Speech," and includes his own thoughts on the subject. Palmer also mentions South Carolina's secession.]
  - William Henry Hurlbert to John Williamson Palmer, 1878 Aug 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Expresses his pleasure with Palmer's poetry in [
    Camp and Canteen Life
    ?].]
  - William Henry Hurlbert to John Williamson Palmer, 1880 Mar 9; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks Palmer for his book, which he looks forward to reading and studying.]
  - Francis Seymour Haden to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Jul 4; ALS, 3 p.
    [Suggests that his contribution to the portfolio correspond in style with "Challow Farm" rather than "Shere Mill Pond" and "Sunset In Ireland," as these go back twenty years in style.]
  - Maxime Lalanne to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Jul 8; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses her plans and the difficulty with the printing plates of the aqua fortis of Trouville; and provides requested information concerning the plate.] in French, with a typed English transcript
  - David Law to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Jul 16; ALS, 3 p.
    [States that the plate will be ready and in Goulding's hands for printing soon; and mentions [Hubert] Herkomer. ] w/typed transcript
  - Frederick Arthur Bridgman to John Williamson Palmer, [1881] Jul 31; ANS, 1 p.
    [Mentions letter from [Charles] Courtry; and regrets he cannot promise Palmer his services.]
  - Alphonse Legros to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Aug 4; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses aqua fortis with a beggar theme which he has just completed.] in French with a typed English transcript
  - Alphonse Legros to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Aug 31; ALS, 4 p.
    [Sends biographical information and promises to send a catalogue of his own etchings and principal paintings.] in French with a typed English transcript
  - Frederick Arthur Bridgman to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Sep 2; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses the work of Lalanne, Lancon and Martial; and sends regards.]
  - Axel Herman Haig to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Sep 4; ALS, 4 p.
    [Sends biographical information and current works; refers to Ewan Christian, William Burges, and Edd. Barry. ] w/typed transcript
  - L. Lancon to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Sep 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Appreciates Palmer's praise for his plate; and asks him to forward the money for it from Boston. ] in French with a typed English transcript
  - Hubert Herkomer to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Sep 16; ALS, 4 p.
    [Sends list of plates and mezzotints; and discusses his experience as an artist.] with etching and typed transcript
  - Ch[arles] Courtry to "Dear Sir", 1881 Oct 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [States that the plate is finished and has been given to Salmon the printer; explains a mix-up in correspondence; and acknowledges the receipt of John Williamson Palmer's payment.] in French with a typed English transcript
  - Arthur Collins to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Oct 24; TL, 1 p.
    [Writing for Princess Louise (Marchioness of Lorne), Collins acknowledges the receipt of the letter and asks Palmer to bring the autograph etchings the following day.]
  - Heywood Hardy to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Oct 31; ALS, 2 p.
    [Acknowledges cheque for sixty-three pounds, sent by Henry F. Gilling. ]
  - James Tissot to John Williamson Palmer, 1881 Dec 2; ALS, 3 p.
    [Sends the proofs for "Two Friends"; inquires about Palmer's work and the success of Tissot's "The Prodigal Son."] in French with a typed English transcript
  - R. H. Chatsworth to [ John Williamson Palmer], 1881 n.m. 15; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he will write the introduction to Palmer's book for free.]
  - W. H. Carpenter to John Williamson Palmer, 1886 Jun 10; ALS, 3 p.
    [Refers to a review of Palmer's book, and
    The Saturday Review
    and discusses the "new school" of novelists including [Henry] James, [William Dean] Howells, and Balzac. ]
  - Helena Modjeska to John Williamson Palmer, 1886 Jun 19; ALS, 2 p.
    [Praises his play The Queen's Heart but regrets that she is unable to produce it; and mentions the enthusiasm of Longfellow, Holmes and Lowell toward the play.]
  - Charles G. D. Hobart to John Williamson Palmer, 1896 Feb 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends autographed copy of "Epitaph for a Husbandman"; and mentions Palmer's poem in
    The Century
    on Theodosia Burr. ]
  - Avander Staal to John Williamson Palmer, 1898 Sep 8; ALS, 1 p.
    [Writing for the Queen of the Netherlands, Staal thanks Palmer for "Orange Boven."] w/a card and typed transcript
  - James T. Fields to John Williamson Palmer, n.y. Mar 13; TL, 1 p.
    [Sends a list of his collection of poems written in the handwriting of twenty-two authors.]
  - Charles H. Webb to John Williamson Palmer, n.y. Mar 31; ALS, 3 p.
    [Makes some critical comments on "the book," an unidentified novel by Palmer.]
  - Lady John Campbell to John Williamson Palmer, n.y. May 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks Palmer for the collection of poems "For Charlie's Sake."]
  - L. Danielli to John Williamson Palmer, n.y. Aug 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks Palmer for an article; and sends two figurines as a gift.] in French, with a typed English transcript
  - Charles H. Webb to John Williamson Palmer, n.y. Nov 12; TL (transcripts), 1 p.
    [Discusses his review of Palmer's book of poetry; and mentions his own new book of verse
    With Lead and Line
    , and the Editor Halsey.]
  - George Grey Barnard to John Williamson Palmer, n.y. Nov 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Offers to show Palmer his statue of "Man."]
  - Francis Seymour Hayden to John Williamson Palmer, n.d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses his pending lecture tour; and refers to [Hubert] Herkomer and [James R.?] Osgood. ]
  - Robert W. MacBeth to John Williamson Palmer, n.d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends etching "The Ferry Inn" with comment on its theme.] w/typed transcript
  - M. Martial to John Williamson Palmer, n.d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends the proofs of aqua fortis
    In the Forest
    . ] in French with a typed English transcript
  - Mrs. Suydaur to John Williamson Palmer, n.d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Gives an elaborate account of an elm tree planted in his honor.]
  - Jules Michelet to John Williamson Palmer, n.d.; ALS, 3 p.
    [Letter written in French, no transcript available.]